Guide to the George E.Crothers Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
George E. Crothers papers
1905-1957
SC0130
Crothers, George E. (George Edward), 1870-1957.
16.5 Linear feet
Correspondence (1905-1957), speeches, articles, legal documents, photographs, newsclippings and scrapbooks. Major subjects include Stanford University, Republican Party activities (1909-1930), California State Normal Schools, United States monetary policy and U.S. relations with the Republic of China (1920-1940). Correspondents include persons prominent in educational and political affairs in the U.S. as well as many leading California lawyers and educators. Also includes correspondence between Crothers and his brother T. G. Crothers relating to Stanford Board of Trustees matters and University legal problems, minutes of the Board (April 1905, May-June 1907), a typescript description of the founding grant and an anonymous diary (1895-1902).
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift of George Crothers to the Stanford Library, 1962; transferred to University Archives, 1975.
Information about Access
This collection is open to researchers with permission of the Stanford University Archives.
Separated Materials
Five framed items were labelled and shelved with the picture collection in the Department of Special Collections:
Photograph or Painting of Jane L. Stanford
Photograph or Painting of George Crothers
Photograph or Painting of Thomas G. Crothers
Printed note to Crothers from student residents of Crothers Hall, Nov. 17, 1951
Letter from Herbert Hoover, copies of which can be found in the Crothers Papers (in "Related correspondence," filed under "Hoover")
These five items were removed in 1962 at the time the collection was first arranged.
In May 1966 Ralph Hansen removed all the Trustee Minutes from the collection (formerly in boxes 17 and 18). These Minutes were added to the group of Trustee Minutes in the University Archives (#1011). Rather than renumber the rest of the boxes in the collection, a note simply was made that Boxes 17 and 18 no longer existed. (For an exact list of the Minutes transferred, see the original 1962 Register filed in the "Crothers" correspondence file in the general files of University Archives.)
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Judge and member of the Stanford Board of Trustees (1902-1912). He served as attorney to Jane Lathrop Stanford and was part donor of two graduate dormitories at Stanford University.
1870 Born (May 27), Wapello, Iowa; son of John and Margaret Jane (Fair) Crothers.
1883 Family moved to San Jose, California. Crothers attends San Jose HighSchool.
1895 Received A.B., Stanford University (in "Pioneer Class").
1896 Received A.M. (in law), Stanford University. Admitted to California Bar.
1897 Formed partnership With brother in San Francisco law practice.
1898 Retained by Mrs. Jane Stanford to write amendment to California State Constitution for purpose of reducing tax burden on University.
1899 Began serving as attorney in Fair Trust case (to 1902). Became president, General Alumni Association of Stanford University. Elected to membership, Golden Gate Commandery # 16, Masonic order. Received Order of Red Cross, Masonic order.
1900 Received Order of Temple, Masonic order.
1902 Became first alumnus to serve on Stanford Univ. Board of Trustees.
1904 Formulated By-Laws & Rules of Order for board of trustees. Devised articles of faculty organization adopted by board of trustees, March 31, 1904
1905 Acted as attorney for board of trustees on death of Jane Stanford. Recomnended establishment of Jewel Fund for acquisition of library books for Stanford University. As chairman, committee on medical education, brought about association of Cooper Medical College with Stanford University.
1909 Became chairman, independent Republican movement, San Francisco. Represented Theodore Roosevelt in urging California Governor & legislators not to undertake land legislation against Orientals.
1911 Married Elizabeth Mills (March 23). Became chairman, Board of Trustees, San Francisco State Normal School. (to 1921)
1912 Became chairman, Republican County Committee (to 1913).
1913 Appointed judge of Superior Court of San Francisco.
1915 Elected to succeed himself on bench by highest vote ever accorded by San Francisco Bar Association.
1916 Resigned as chairman of Republican County Committee.
1919 Served as presiding judge of Superior Court.
1920 Wife, Elizabeth, died (August 18).
1921 Returned to active practice of law.
1924 Made a summer tour of Europe.
1932 Published article, "Outline of History of Founding of Stanford University".
1933 Delivered speech, "Educational Ideals of Jane Lathrop Stanford"
1946 Announced he would help to finance building of graduate dormitory for law students to be called "Crothers Hall"•
1948 Completion and dedication of Crothers Hall.
1951 Two new wings added to Crothers Hall.
1953 Announced he would help to finance building of graduate dormitory for engineering students to be dedicated to his mother, Margaret Jane Fair Crothers, and to be called "Crothers Memorial Hall".
1955 Completion and dedication of Crothers Memorial Hall.
1957 Died, May 16.
Memberships: California Historical Society, American Law Institute, American Political Science Association, Schoolmaster's Club of California, Stanford Faculty Club, Commercial Club, Commonwealth Club, Marin Country Club, Pacific Union Club, University Club of San Francisco, Monterey Peninsula Country Club, American Historical Association, Sigma Nu, Phi Delta Phi, Burlingame Country Club, San Francisco Opera Guild, American Geographic Society.
Honorary trustee, San Francisco Boys Club.
Director, Western States Life Insurance Company.
Life trustee, Leland Stanford Junior Kindergarten Trust.
For further reference see Container # 13 for biographical data concerning George Crothers.
Description of the Collection
The Crothers Papers contain George Crothers' correspondence dated from 1905-1957. The bulk of the outgoing correspondence was written between 1930 and 1955. The collection also includes manuscript and typescript copies of Crothers' speeches, articles, legal documents, photographs, newsclippings and scrapbooks and memoranda, as well as printed matter collected by Crothers.
Of primary interest are Crothers' writings on his alma mater, Stanford University, which he served as attorney for Jane Stanford, as member of the university 's Board of Trustees, and as part-donor of two graduate dormitories. The collection also includes materials concerning United States relations with the Republic of China, c. 1920-1940; Republican party activities, c. 1909-1930; California State Normal Schools; and United States economic affairs and monetary policy, c. 1920-40.
Correspondents include persons prominent in educational and political affairs in the United States, as well as a large number of leading California lawyers and educators. Also includes correspondence between Crothers and his brother T. G. Crothers relating to Stanford Board of Trustees matters and University legal problems, minutes of the Board (April 1905, May-June 1907), a typescript description of the founding grant and an anonymous diary (1895-1902).A partial list of the correspondents is included in the Register.
Access Terms
Abbott, Nathan, 1854-1941; Boynton, Albert E.; Burk, Frederic, 1862-1924.; Carpenter, Thomas P.; Chandler, Harry.; Considine, John W.; Coolidge, Calvin, 1872-1933.; Cowley, W. H. (William Harold), 1899-1978; Crothers, George E. (George Edward), 1870-1957.; Cubberley, Ellwood Patterson, 1868-1941; Cutler, Leland W. (Leland Whitman), 1885-1959.; Dailey, M. E.; Davis, Horace, 1831-1916; Dern, George T.; Dinkelspiel, Lloyd W.; Downs, Winfield Scott, 1895-; Dunn, Francis.; Edwards, Paul C., (Paul Carroll), 1882-1962.; Eells, Walter C.; Elliott, Orrin Leslie, 1860-1940; Eurich, Alvin C., (Alvin Christian), 1902-1987.; French, Will J. (Will John), b. 1871; Fuller, W. Palmer.; Gerberding, Elizabeth.; Gunst, Morgan.; Hassett, William D., 1880-1965.; Hayes, J. O.; Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964; Hopkins, Timothy, 1859-1937.; Howe, Louis M. (Louis McHenry), 1871-1936.; Hughes, Charles Evans, 1862-1948.; James, William, 1842-1910; Johnson, Hiram, 1866-1945; Jones, Herbert C. (Herbert Coffin), 1881-1970.; Jordan, David Starr, 1851-1931; Keesling, Francis V. (Francis Valentine), 1877-1963; Kefauver, Grayson Neikirk, 1900-1946.; Kirkwood, Marion.; Lane, Arthur Bliss.; Lane, Franklin K.; Leib, Samuel F. 1848-1924.; Lillick, Ira.; Lurie, Louis R.; MacArthur, Walter.; Morell, George, 1786-1845.; Neylan, John Francis.; Norman, R. S.; Older, Fremont, Mrs., 1875-1968; Osborne, George.; Reid, Whitelaw, 1837-1912.; Republican Party (U.S.); Robinson, Edgar Eugene, 1887-1977; Rogers, Frederick Rand, 1894-; Roseberry, L. H.; Shortridge, Samuel Morgan, b. 1861.; Simpson, Sidney Post, 1898-1949.; Sinclair, Upton, 1878-1968; Spaeth, Carl B.; Spreckels, Rudolph.; Sproul, Robert Gordon.; Stanford University. Board of Trustees.; Stanford University. Crother's Hall.; Stanford, Jane Lathrop, 1828-1905.; Stanford, Thomas Welton, 1832-1918.; Stephens, William D.; Sterling, J. E. Wallace, (John Ewart Wallace), 1906-1985; Stone, Harlan Fiske, 1872-1946.; Swain, Robert E. (Robert Eccles), 1875-1961.; Terman, Frederick Emmons, 1900-1982; Tresidder, Donald Bertrand, 1894-1948; Warren, Earl, 1891-1974.; White, Andrew Dickson,, 1832-1918.; Wilbur, Curtis D.; Wilbur, Ray L., (Ray Lyman), 1875-1949; Articles.; China--Foreign relations--United States; Judges.; Lawyers.; Monetary policy --United States.; Newsclippings.; Photoprints.; Scrapbooks; Speeches.; United States--Foreign relations; United States--Foreign relations--China
Collection Contents
- Correspondence, Series I
  Boxes 1-4. Outgoing correspondence. Yellow tabs; in 95 folders. Letters of George Crothers; arranged chronologically, April, 1905- April, 1957.
  Boxes 5-8. Incoming correspondence. Blue tabs; in 95 folders. Letters to George Crothers; arranged alphabetically by author of item and chronologically under each signer.
  Box 8. Related correspondence. Red tabs; in 12 folders. Letters neither sent by Crothers nor sent to him. Filed alphabetically by author of item.
  Box 9. Form letters. White tabs; in 13 folders. Mimeographed, dittoed or printed letters received by Crothers although not directed to Crothers alone. Filed alphabetically by author of item or by title of company, etc.
  Boxes 9-12. Multiple copies of outgoing correspondence. Yellow tabs marked "copies"; in 73 folders. These letters are merely duplicates of letters found in Containers #l-4
  Box 12. Multiple copies of incoming correspondence. Blue tabs marked "copies"; in 15 folders. These letters are merely duplicates of letters found in Containers #5-8
  Box 12. Multiple copies of related correspondence. Red tabs marked "copies"; in 4 folders. These letters are merely duplicates of letters in folders with red tabs found in Container #8.
  - Correspondence, out-going., 1905 Apr - 1923 Dec (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, out-going., 1924 Jan - 1939 Dec (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, out-going., 1940 Feb - 1947 Dec (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, out-going., 1948 Jan - 1957 Apr (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, in-coming. A - G (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, in-coming. H - M (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, in-coming. N - Sterling (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, in-coming. Stillman - Z. (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, related. A - Y (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, in-coming (form letters) A - Y (Box 9)
  - Correspondence, multiple copies of out-going., 1905-30 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence, multiple copies of out- going., 1931-44 (Box 10)
  - Correspondence, multiple copies of out-going., 1945-50 (Box 11)
  - Correspondence, multiple copies of out-going., 1951-56 (Box 12)
  - Correspondence, multiple copies of in-coming. A - Y (Box 12)
  - Correspondence, multiple copies of related. A - W (Box 12)
- Biographical Data, Series II
  White tabs; in 16 folders. Manuscript and typescript material containing biographical data concerning Nathan Abbott, Elizabeth Mills Crothers, George Crothers, William Filmer, Timothy Hopkins, Jane and Leland Stanford, Leland Stanford, Jr. and Ray Lyman Wilbur. Arranged in alphabetical order under the subject personality.
  - Biographical data; Abbott - Willbur. (Box 13)
- Speeches, Series III
  Green tabs; in 68 folders. Manuscript, typescript, and, in a few cases, printed versions of speeches composed by George Crothers, Herbert Hoover, Jane Stanford and others. The speeches are filed first alphabetically by the name of the author-speaker and then chronologically by date of speech. The bulk of the section contains copies of Crothers' speeches between 1907 and 1951. Many speeches concern the founding of Stanford University and the school's early years. See also published addresses included in section entitled "printed matter."
  - Speeches: Branner - Crothers, to 1910 (Box 13)
  - Speeches: Crothers, 1911-46 (Box 14)
  - Speeches: Crothers - Stanford, Jane, 1948 - undated (Box 15)
- Articles, Series IV
  Red tabs; in 20 folders. Manuscript and typescript copies of articles by Crothers and others. Filed alphabetically by author and then chronologically by year of the article. Eight folders contain various drafts, copies and outlines of an article by Crothers on the legal history surrounding the early years of Stanford University.
  - Articles: Crothers - Smith (Box 16)
- Stanford University Board of Trustees. Transactions., Series V
  Blue tabs; in 28 folders. Manuscript and typescript versions of memoranda, committee reports, lists of degrees, etc., pertinent to the work of the Stanford Board of Trustees during the years from 1903 to 1912. Arranged alphabetically by the subject of the material. A large bulk of the section deals with data collected by Crothers and compiled in 1908 as a study of entrance requirements in colleges and universities throughout the United States.
  - Stanford Board of Trustees transactions. (Box 19)
    Subjects covered: Alumni - Stanford, Jane.
- Memoranda regarding Stanford University., Series VI
  Orange tabs; in 52 folders. Manuscript and typescript versions of memoranda written by Crothers and others concerning Stanford University. Arranged alphabetically by subject. Contains reminiscenses concerning campus life, notes on religion at Stanford, and financial data and notes on Crothers and Crothers Memorial Halls.
  - Stanford University, memoranda re. (Box 20)
    Subjects covered: Administration - Founding Grant.
  - Stanford University, memoranda re. (Box 21)
    Subjects covered: Harrison, Benjamin - Tuition.
- General Memoranda., Series VII
  Green tabs; in 15 folders. Manuscript or typescript versions of memoranda written by or collected by George Crothers. Arranged alphabetically by subject. Folder #11 contains office memoranda. Folders #12-#15 contain fragmentary memoranda.
  - General memoranda. (Box 21)
    Subjects covered: Education - US political affairs.
- Organizational Data., Series VIII
  Yellow tabs; in 13 folders. Manuscript and typescript material re. organizations to which Crothers belonged. Arranged alphabetically by type of data (e.g., legislation, minutes).
  - Organization data (Box 22)
- Legal Material., Series IX
  White tabs; in 16 folders. Manuscript and typescript data of a strictly legal nature. Arranged alphabetically by type of document (e.g., case studies, leases). Most of the documents in this section concern Stanford University. Included is a photostatic copy of Jane Stanford's will.
  - legal material (Box 22)
- Extracts., Series X
  Orange tabs; in 21 folders. Manuscript and typescript excerpts from various books, documents, speeches, etc., written by Crothers and others. Arranged alphabetically by type of data (e.g., books) from which excerpts are drawn.
  - Extracts (Box 23)
- Miscellaneous Data., Series XI
  Green tabs; in 18 folders. Material of a miscellaneous nature. Includes bills, receipts, certificates, etc.
  - Miscellaneous data (Box 23)
- Plans & Designs., Series XII
  Yellow tabs; in 13 folders. Various architectural plans and artistic designs. Filed alphabetically by type of data. The bulk of the section contains designs for Crothers Hall and Crothers Hemorial Hall at Stanford University.
  - Architectural plans and designs. (Box 24)
- Photographs., Series XIII
  Red tabs; in 21 folders. First 8 folders contain photographic portraits and snapshots with one person as subject. Filed alphabetically by name of subject. Folders #9-12 contain photographs of large groups or snapshots at memorable occasions. Filed chronologically by date of photo. Folders #13-19 contain general photographs and pictures of landscapes and buildings. Filed alphabetically by subject of photograph. In the last section much of the material concerns Crothers Hall and Crothers Memorial Hall. Folder #20 contains miscellaneous negatives.
  - Personal photographs (Box 24)
    Arranged alphabetically by subject: Crothers - Stanford.
  - Group photographs; general photographs; negatives (Box 25)
- Newspaper Clippings., Series XIV
  Blue tabs; in 38 folders. Divided into two sections: 1) clippings re Stanford University, 2) general clippings. All of the clippings are arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Newspaper clippings re. Stanford University. (Box 25)
    Subjects, arranged alphabetically: Administration - Presidents.
  - Newspaper clippings re. Stanford University. (Box 26)
    Subjects, arranged alphabetically: Religion - student affairs.
  - Newspaper clippings on general subjects. (Box 26)
    Subjects, arranged alphabetically: California - World Affairs.
- Printed Matter., Series XV
  Orange tabs. Folders are not numbered consecutively, because material is often too large to permit storage in file folders.
  Box 27. Books, booklets, bound articles,legal data.
  Box 28. Unbound articles, published addresses, directories, reports, pamphlets.
  Box 29. Periodicals, magazines, bulletins.
  Box 30. Commemorative data (e.g., programs, invitations) and miscellaneous.
  - Printed matter: Books, booklets, bound articles, legal data. (Box 27)
  - Printed matter: unbound articles, addresses, pamphlets, directories. (Box 28)
  - Printed matter: periodicals, magazines, bulletins. (Box 29)
  - Printed matter: commemorative data and newspapers. (Box 30)
- Scrapbooks & Albums., Series XVI
  This material is not boxed. Container numbers run consecutively from one bound volume to the next.
  - Scrapbook of miscellaneous news clippings (Box 31)
  - Scrapbook containing clippings of "The Story of Stanford University" (Box 32)
  - Scrapbook containing further clippings of "The Story of Stanford University" (Box 33)
  - Album of photographs concerning the construction of Crothers Hall (Box 34)
  - Notebook containing photostatic copy of memoirs concerning Battle of Santiago, 1898 (Box 35)
- Oversized Materials., Series XVII
  - Wrapped package (Box 36)
    Stored in wrapping paper. Contains printed copies of 1) Statute for Permanent Court of International Justice, 2) "The Christmas Wasp"; photographs of G. E. Crothers, Herbert Hoover, Charles G. Lathrop, David Starr Jordan, George Osborne and Crothers Hall; various awards and certificates.